All right.
Let's get started.
So last time, Tatsu talked about scaling laws,
and we're going to take a little break from that
and talk about inference.
So the problem of inference is very simple.
You've trained a model, and you're given a prompt,
and you want to produce the response usually
as accurately and as quickly as you can.
So inference turns out to be only one lecture,
but it's actually of growing importance.
And it shows up in many places.
So clearly, once you've trained a model,
you don't just sit there.
And if you're a researcher, you put
a plot in your paper of here's how my model works,
but for everyone else, you actually want to use this model.
So what does use look like?
It could be chatting with an AI assistant or chatbot,
it could be doing code completion.
These days, agents are very popular,
and that requires inference.
Batch data processing as well.
It's also used for evaluation.
For evaluation that requires generation in particular.
And it's also used inside training.
If you're doing reinforcement learning,
you need to have a model, you generate rollouts,
and you score them, and you update the weights appropriately.
So inference shows up all over the place.
And efficiency, as is the theme of this class,
really matters more than ever here.
And even if you just look at the actual use app of vantage point,
training is a one-time cost.
It could be very expensive.
It is very expensive.
But once you're done with it, that's it.
But inference is a repeated cost.
You kind of incur them every single day.
So OpenAI is estimated to produce 8.6 trillion tokens a day.
And just for reference, DeepSeek-V4,
which came out earlier this year,
was trained on 32 trillion tokens.
So in less than four days, the number of tokens
that OpenAI has to produce, and therefore the compute
is at least DeepSeek-V4.
And of course, even the frontier models
might be trained on more tokens, but still,
inference, the number of tokens generated is going to be higher.
So that's just some perspective.
And moreover, I think the importance of inference
has grown in the last year because once upon a time,
we thought of language models as primarily
as chatbots or assistants, where you put in a prompt,
you get back a response, and presumably,
the goal of the human is to read the response.
But now, as we move more into an agentic world,
what it looks like is that a query goes in,
and the agent is going to do a bunch of stuff.
It's going to think, it's going to reason,
it's going to call some tools, it's going to introspect.
And at the end of the day, it will produce some output
for a human to read.
So most of the tokens that the agent produces
is actually not for reading.
And so you should really think about the number
of tokens generated as really the compute spend.
And there's no limit.
If you have an ambitious enough problem,
you're going to need much compute and a lot of tokens.
So if you were in the chatbot world,
maybe inference after a certain point,
it's fast enough, because humans can only read so fast.
But for an agent, there's no limit to how much a value
you can get out of squeezing more out of inference.
So there's a lot of people doing inference
on the commercial side.
Of course, all the closed API providers
have to serve their models, so inference
is a big deal for them.
And there is also a bunch of providers
serving open-weight models and providing inference as well.
And in the open source community,
there's a bunch of packages.
So vLLM is probably a popular one.
Kind of a go-to.
SGLang is another one that's particularly
good for agentic workloads, but maybe not as popular yet.
And then there's TensorRT from NVIDIA, which is really fast,
but it's more narrow.
And then llama.cpp, if you want to run inference on CPU,
this is a popular package.
So hopefully, I've argued that inference is huge.
If you can make inference twice as fast or even 10% faster,
that is a big deal.
So now, the question is, what does fast mean?
So there's a few metrics that capture the notion of fast.
And they're going to be applicable in different settings
and have different trade-offs.
So one metric of fast is time to first token or TTFT.
This is essentially how long a user waits
before any generation happens.
So you put in a query into ChatGPT,
and some number of milliseconds passes by, and then
from the point the first token comes in, that is the time.
And this is generally useful for interactive applications
because that latency where you're just waiting and doing
nothing is--
the longer that is, the worse the user experience,
and as soon as tokens come in, it doesn't maybe
have to be that fast, because if you're going to read it anyway,
you can't read that fast.
So the second metric is latency.
And this is from the standpoint of an individual user.
How fast are tokens appearing for one query?
This is also important for interactive applications.
So basically, this is how fast the tokens are kind of streaming
through.
And then the second related concept
is throughput, measuring tokens per second,
This is how fast tokens are appearing for many queries.
So latency, or one latency, and throughput
are clearly very related.
It's very kind of aligned. In general,
many interventions will make latency and throughput better.
But as we'll see later, there's actually a trade-off here.
And throughput is useful for if you're doing
a bunch of batch processing.
You have a petabyte of data, and you
want to process it with a language model.
You just want that job to get done.
It doesn't matter if one query is coming in faster, sooner,
or later.
OK.
So what determines the efficiency
by any of these metrics of inference?
So the high-level bit is as follows.
And this is maybe one high-level bit
to remember from the lecture: that when you're doing training,
you see all the tokens at once, because
in supervised fine-tuning, you see all the tokens,
and you can parallelize over the sequence.
Remember, think about in the transformer,
the calculation for attention, MLP,
the sequence is just a dimension.
So it's a big tensor that gets multiplied.
And so you essentially process all the tokens at once.
In inference, you can't do that.
You have to generate because of the autoregressive nature
of inference,
tokens sequentially,
one at a time.
So this is the fundamental problem
of why inference is a very different workload
than training, because you can't parallelize across the sequence
dimension.
And therefore, as we'll see later,
it's going to be harder to have high arithmetic intensity
or fully utilize the compute.
OK.
All right.
So let's go on.
So first, I'm going to-- just maybe a preview of what's
in this lecture.
First, I'm going to do some math to understand the arithmetic
intensity and throughput and latency,
how to think about that for a transformer.
And then I'm going to talk about various techniques
to reduce the cost by making the KV cache smaller,
quantizing model pruning, and then
finally, I'll talk about speculative decoding, and then
some kind of practical concerns.
All right.
So this is going to be a bit of a review, mostly
kind of swapping in, making sure we're
on the same page with respect to notation.
Much of this lecture is based on the scaling book from Google
on transformers and inference.
So I do recommend that people go check it out.
It's a very nicely written.
And some of the figures are generously lifted from that book.
OK.
So just to establish a bit of notation
to understand this diagram.
So we're going to use symbols.
Think about it in einops to denote dimensions,
but also they're kind of length.
So B is going to be the batch dimension and also
the number of sequences.
T is going to be the sequence dimension, which
is also the number of tokens.
D is the model dimension, H is the dimension.
So if I'm going to write this, this taking a product between a tensor with dimensions B, T,
and D, and another matrix of D and H, and I produce BTH.
So what is going on here is that there
are some dimensions marked red, which
are going to be contracting.
These dimensions appear in both the operands
and disappear from the results.
And then there's going to be other regular dimensions
in black that appear only in one operand and stay in the result.
So this is the general form.
Another case is if you have blue dimensions, that
means they're attaching dimensions,
and they appear in both, but stay in the result.
They do not get contracted or reduced.
OK.
So the interpretation here, as we'll see later,
is that we have this tensor for every sequence
and token position.
You have a vector and you want to multiply that by a matrix.
And then here, you're basically taking
a bunch of dot products between two tensors.
OK.
So with that in mind, this in all its full glory,
is the description of a transformer block.
So it looks a little bit like a circuit diagram.
There's a lot of details here, but I actually
find this probably the most crisp definition
of what a transformer is.
You see a lot of description of transformer,
and frankly, a lot of them are-- it's
hard to understand what is exactly happening.
This one basically tells you exactly the shapes
of the tensors and allows you to reason about the dependency.
So for transformer block, you take
the X, which is the activations of one layer,
you feed it through a tension, and then
you feed it through MLP.
And just as a kind of a quick refresher,
you projected using a query matrix, a key matrix and a value
matrix, you'll see here that we have
N, which is the number of heads, and H
is the dimension of each head.
So the query matrix is batch times sequence times number
of heads times the head dimension,
and K and V, instead of having N,
we have K, which we'll see later,
which we have a potentially smaller number key value heads.
And then this is the attention operation,
where notice that there's batching dimensions.
So B appears in both.
And we're contracting over the head dimension.
And we'll come back to why this B, B in both,
makes inference hard.
Why attention is kind of a bottleneck there.
So just hold on to that thought.
And the MLP is very simple and straightforward.
You just do some math models.
This is the gating matrix.
This is the upper direction and a down projection.
So thank you guys.
I have implemented this.
So I don't want to belabor it, but just
to swap in the notation.
By convention, we're going to assume that in the MLP,
the MLP up projects the D dimensional, model dimension
into four times that.
So F is always--think about it as 4D whenever you see F.
And then the model dimension gets split across the N heads.
So the model dimension is always equal to number of heads
times the head dimension.
And then the number of heads get split,
in the case of group query attention,
into the number of groups and the number of heads per group.
And finally, we have two variables, S and T,
which both represents the sequence dimension.
And the difference is that S is going
to represent the number of input tokens,
and T is going to represent the number of output tokens.
So in training time, these two are the same,
because we're predicting all the same inputs as outputs.
And inference time, T is going to be 1,
and S is going to be the input.
OK.
So another review for arithmetic intensity.
So I talked about this in the second lecture.
So just as a warm up.
Suppose I'm multiplying two matrices; a B by D
matrix and a D by F matrix.
So intuition.
B is the batch dimension, D is the hidden dimension
or the model dimension, and F is the projection dimension
in the MLP.
So remember, what is the arithmetic intensity?
I have to count flops, and I have
to count the amount of memory moved.
So we can do this as follows.
So what do you have to do to multiply these matrices?
Now, remember, the systems lectures,
you have to read X from HBM.
And if you're storing everything in bf16,
which is the case for inference, we're
going to have 2 times B times D, you're going to read W. That's
going to be another 2 times D times F.
You're going to do the matmul.
So the number of flops is 2 times B times D times F
And then you're going to write it back.
OK?
So every time you read and write,
it's basically the number of entries.
It's kind of a quadratic-like term, and matmuls are cubic.
And remember, this is going to be important
because that's how you're going to get high arithmetic
intensity.
So the total number of flops is the cubic,
and then the bytes transferred is the sum of the reads
and writes.
So remember, arithmetic intensity is how much compute
we do per byte transfer.
And we want this to be high.
So the intensity is going to be equal to flops
over bytes transferred.
And I'm representing all these things symbolically,
because it will be easier to see and work
with rather than numbers.
One simplification we can make
is that suppose that the batch dimension here
is much less than D and F, then we can simplify this.
So in particular, what this is doing is saying D equals C
times D and F equals C times B and let C goes to infinity,
so both D and F are really large and B is smaller,
and this just reduces to the intensity of B.
So the upshot of that is that remember
when we did arithmetic intensity for matmul,
it was something like N/3.
And this is the kind of analog, where
instead of just having square matrices,
we have non-square matrices.
OK.
So just to compare, so the accelerator intensity
of a hardware is you look at the flops per second
in the spec sheet, you look at how much memory bandwidth, how
fast memory gets moved between HBM, you divide,
and that is the accelerated intensity.
And now, you compare your computations intensity
with your accelerator intensity.
And if it's greater then your compute bound, which is good,
if you're less, then you're memory bound, and that's bad.
So in this case, for H100, for this particular matmul
operation, you're compute bound if the batch
size is greater than 295.
So here's an extreme case.
So suppose you just have one example.
What happens is you have one example, then
your arithmetic intensity is going to be one.
And this is going to be memory bound.
And you can see what's going on here.
You're reading this DF matrix, but B is only one.
So you're effectively doing only 2 times D times F flops.
And this is basically the workload
that you'll see in inference.
You don't get these full matrices,
you get these very thin matrices or tensors.
OK.
Let me stop there in case there's any questions.
Yeah.
In the transformer slide, I just want to confirm [INAUDIBLE].
You said, across [INAUDIBLE] can search across [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, should that be across tables instead of cubes?
Let's see.
So the number of groups here is—wait, I'm just making sure.
So K is the number of key value heads.
And so you have g per KV head.
My understanding is [INAUDIBLE] each key path will have one
[INAUDIBLE] correspond to it.
And [INAUDIBLE] then g is the number of [INAUDIBLE] p.
That means we have k.
That's my question.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, I think you're right.
So k should be the number of groups,
and g should be the number of heads per one
of those groups.
Yes.
Yeah, OK.
Thanks for that.
I'll fix that later.
OK.
So let's talk a little bit more about the arithmetic
intensity of inference.
So here's how to think about what's happening in inference.
Let's say you just do it naively.
So here is a prompt never going to give you.
I'm going to the transformer.
And the transformer generates keys and values
and activations.
And at the end of the day, it generates logits
over the output vocabulary.
And you sample a token, and that token
gets concatenated with the prompt,
and then you just do this again.
You generate never.
You attach that to the prompt and so on and so forth.
So this is the most naive thing.
If you have a black box that takes a sequence
and outputs a distribution over tokens, which
is exactly what a transformer does,
you can just apply this repeatedly.
OK, so this works, but this is really bad because each time you
generate one token, you actually take
order T squared time where T is the number of tokens
that you've generated so far.
So generating T tokens is actually T cubed because the attention is
already T squared, and you have to do that once for every token.
So this is pretty bad, but the observation
is that you don't actually have to do this.
A lot of the work can actually be shared across prefixes.
So for example, if you're generating network versus you're
generating up, you're actually computing
a lot of the same key values for never going to give.
So these tokens, they shouldn't change, OK?
And this is because it's a causal transformer.
If it was bidirectional, then if you attach a token,
then everything changes.
But if it's causal, then the activations
here don't change based on any tokens you append.
So with that observation, the first obvious thing
is to store a KV cache in HBM, so
that, between successive token generations,
you can just reuse the KV cache.
So that means when you are trying to generate a token, you
don't actually have to compute all the keys and activations
of these previous tokens.
So this is what it looks like with a KV cache.
So there's going to be two stages: pre-fill.
So you get the prompt, and you populate the KV cache, which
is the set of key and value pairs that the transformer computes,
and then you generate the logits--
just the same computation as we did before.
And now you have the KV cache here and then this distribution
which you sample a token.
And now you feed that through the transformer, which
uses this cache and then produces
both the distribution of the next tokens,
but a new KV, which is basically activations
corresponding to the token up.
And then this gets fed in.
So now you have the updated KV cache.
You have this logits you sample, and then that
feeds to the transformer.
You output the distribution over next tokens
as well as the new token which you add to the KV cache
and so on and so forth.
So the KV cache formula is for every sequence--
so there's B of them.
For every token, there's S of them.
And for every layer and every head,
you store H dimensional vector.
And just to reiterate for inference, there's prefill.
You're given a prompt.
You encode the prompt into these vectors.
And this is parallelizable just like in training
because you see the entire prompt.
You can compute the KV cache.
And then in generation, you generate the new response tokens
sequentially.
But at least you don't have to pay
for generating the KV cache of the tokens
that you already looked at.
So is everyone comfortable with the KV cache?
Any questions about this?
All right, so let's try to figure out the FLOPs and memory
I/O for both MLP and attention layers.
So remember S is the number of tokens
we're kind of conditioning on, and T is the number of tokens
we're generating.
So we're going to do this abstractly.
And then later, we'll specify to the prefill where T equals S,
and generation T equals 1.
So for the MLP layers-- and through all of this,
I'm just going to look at the matmul
because the matmuls are the thing that
actually require a lot of work.
Everything else is not that many FLOPs
and can be potentially fused into the matmul too.
OK.
So let's do this calculation.
So it's the same as the matrix calculations.
I'm not going to maybe belabor the step through every single detail
here, but just the form is you read X
from high bandwidth memory.
You read all the parameters.
You compute the upper projection,
and then you write it to HBM.
You compute the gate, and you write HBM,
and then you compute basically the down projection of that,
and you write it to HBM.
So the number of flops depends on B and T
and D and F. So batch size, sequence length,
model dimension, and the feedforward dimension,
MLP dimension.
And the bytes transferred is this expression.
So now you can compute the arithmetic intensity
which, again, is FLOPs divided by bytes transferred.
So this is some expression.
We're going to assume, that just like before, B times T
is much smaller than D and F. And with that, then we see
that intensity is B times T.
So this is analogous to just the MAmmoTH case.
There's more matrices and there's more dimensions,
but fundamentally it's the same thing.
And that makes sense.
An MLP is basically a big MAmmoTH.
And it also makes sense because the batch dimension
and the sequence length dimension are--
everything is independent.
And for the MLP, they don't interact.
Attention is different story.
And so B times T. So as long as you have--
in the pre-fill, if you make B times T
large enough-- large batches, long sequences-- you'll be fine.
Now, let's look at generation.
So remember, generation, there's two problems here.
One is that generation T equals 1.
You're only generating one token at a time.
And so that means your arithmetic intensity
is going to be B, but B in generation
is the number of concurrent requests.
And so if you're in a batch setting, you can control that.
But if you're, let's say, serving a chatbot,
it's the number of concurrent requests
is essentially how many users, concurrent users there are?
Which can be high.
It can be low.
So it's a bit unpredictable.
It can be changing over time.
So that's something we're going to address when we
talk about continuous batching.
But overall, this is not bad because as long
as you have large batches, the sequence length
isn't going to really help you.
But if you have large batches, you should be good.
So now let's look at the attention layer.
So again, S is the previous tokens already generated.
T is the number of tokens you want to generate logits for.
So in attention, you read the QKV matrices from HBM.
You compute the attention.
You compute the softmax which doesn't really matter,
and compute the value matrix, and then you
write the result to HBM.
So the FLOPs is B times S times T times D,
and the bytes transferred is this expression.
Everything is a matmul, right?
So this should be always one degree higher of a polynomial
than the bytes transferred because it's a matmul.
The only question is, what does that factor look like?
So that factor for attention is S times T over S plus T.
So let's look at the prefill.
So prefill, what this is saying is
that the prefill intensity is S over 2 when T equals
S. So this is good, right?
Because as long as you have long sequence lengths for attention,
you're going to maintain high arithmetic intensity.
Notice that the batching dimension doesn't happen here.
I'll explain a bit why later.
But for generation, this is bad news.
So the generation intensity is S over S plus 1,
and that's less than 1, or even let's just call it 1.
And arithmetic intensity, remember 1 is bad.
We want it to be something like 295 for H100
to be able to saturate the compute.
And so this is really the bottleneck.
So we did all this analysis for MLP attention,
prefilled generation, and we've found this to be a bottleneck.
So let's try to contemplate why this is a bottleneck.
So unlike MLPs-- so MLP is for generation is actually OK
as long as your sequence is--
sorry, your batch is large enough.
So the problem with this MLP attention is that--
let's look at MLPs.
Every sequence hits the same MLP weights.
So these don't depend on B. Whereas, in attention layer,
each sequence has its own KV cache.
So these all depend on MLP.
And so you can think about this as what's going on here
is that in the MLP case, having B being big actually
is helpful because you get to load these MLP weights once.
And you can use it for all your sequences.
That's how you get high arithmetic intensity
because you use it--simplifying a bit, you load it once.
You do all your batch processing, and then that is good.
Whereas, in attention, all these depend on B. So increasing B
doesn't help.
It's like for every sequence, you're
basically doing a matmul.
So they're all independent.
So doing more matmuls isn't helpful.
Just if you remember in the very beginning,
I showed you this example.
This also has pretty bad arithmetic intensity.
It's not a matmul because we're essentially
batching by a coordinate.
And this is essentially basically the same
as doing a dot product, which has horrible arithmetic
intensity.
And remember, this is in the attention.
This blue B is the cause of why the attention is
arithmetic intensity doesn't scale with B,
and why that is a bottleneck.
So just to summarize here.
So prefill is compute-bound.
Generation is memory-bound.
So if you look at the MLP intensity for prefill,
it's B times S, great.
Prefill for attention, intensity S over 2--
not as good, but workable.
Generation MLP intensity, also workable,
requires long concurrent requests.
But it is really the generation attention
intensity which is a fundamental bottleneck, and that's it.
If you're sticking with a transformer,
you can't really improve this.
OK.
Pause there for questions.
So now whenever you hear people say, oh, inference
is memory bound, you know why.
OK.
So let's now use these intuitions and calculations
to think about our inference metrics
throughput and latency and also TFRT.
All right.
So inference is memory bound.
Now the main-- I mean, in some ways
this simplifies a lot of things because when
we think about how long things take,
you just look at how much memory needs to be transferred, OK?
Because assuming you overlap communication and computation,
the bottleneck is going to be just the amount of memory
that you have to deal with.
So in some ways, it's nice because it's simpler.
But in other ways, it's frustrating
that your accelerators are sitting there not doing anything.
So let's walk through an example.
So for Llama 2.13B on an H100.
So what is the latency and the throughput?
So remember Llama 2.13B has a particular shape.
So this is a sequence length, the model dimension,
feedforward dimension, number of query, number key value heads.
There's no GQA here.
So N equals k, head dimension,
number of layers, vocab size, and the memory bandwidth
for H100.
So now, using this config, let's compute
the transformer performance statistics, OK?
So these are our inputs here.
And just the statistics I'm going to compute
are going to be number of parameters, the memory usage,
latency, and throughput.
So first of all, what takes memory?
So the parameters take memory.
So we compute the number of parameters.
And so you look at the embeddings, the MLP layers,
the projections of the KQV.
At the end of the day, you get some number of parameters.
Assuming that we're doing a bf16, which is always
the case for inference, then parameters
take up this many bytes.
Also in memory is the KV cache.
And the KV cache is the number of tokens in your sequence
times the number of heads and the KV heads times the head
dimension times the number of layers.
You have one for the key and one for the value,
and then you have multiple two for bf16.
So that's the size of the KV cache.
And the total memory usage is--
this is for each sequence you have B sequences.
So that's B times that plus the parameter size.
And that's the amount of memory you need.
And now, what's the latency?
The latency is determined by the memory I/O, OK?
Because inference is memory-bound, most assuming you
overlap communication and compute.
All the memory, it's going to be on shuffling parameters back
and forth between HBM and SRAM.
So that's how long it takes to move memory around.
Throughput is the inverse of latency,
but we're generating B tokens in parallel.
So this is tokens per second.
This is seconds per token.
This is tokens per second, as well as
having an additional B because you're processing a batch of B.
So now, let's compute for this config what
are these actual values?
So num parameters is 13 billion.
So a good sanity check-- that is advertised as a 13 billion
parameter model.
Memory is this term, which is about 838 million times B.
So it's basically a linear function
of B plus some other term.
So this is a KV cache which grows
as B. This is the parameters, which
is double the number of params.
Now, latency is just this scale by the memory bandwidth,
so it has the same form as the memory.
And throughput is B over that.
So notice that latency, as you increase B,
grows because the KV cache grows.
And in order to process stuff, you
have to copy the KV cache back and forth.
And now, throughput is more interesting
because, as you increase B, throughput
does improve but up to a limit.
Throughput improves because now you're
amortizing the cost over a larger batch.
But also, the speed at which you're processing this obviously
is also increasing over time.
So this asymptotes.
It's not going to--throughput can't possibly go to infinity.
Any questions about this so far?
So basically, you just have to remember
latency is a linear function in B. This is where the constant is
the size of KV cache, and then this the number of parameters.
And then throughput is some proportional to B over B
plus something.
So now, let's instantiate this for a bunch of situations, OK?
So if you have batch size 1, so this is what you would get.
You get a latency of 0.008 seconds per token.
And the throughput is 124 tokens per second.
So what happens if you increase the batch size,
you'll see that the latency goes up,
but the throughput also goes up.
So latency gets worse, but the throughput improves.
So this is an interesting thing because we think about, oh, we
just want to make it go fast.
But fast actually has two meanings
here, which actually, depending on which one you care about,
is completely opposite.
If you want to tune your batch size,
that's going to really determine if you
want latency or throughput.
And what happens if you increase-- let's say, increase--
we really want high throughput because we're
processing lots of documents.
Let's increase the batch size even more, OK?
So the latency gets even worse.
I mean, yeah, it gets worse.
Throughput gets even better.
But the main problem here is that your memory, you run out
of memory because the memory, for storing this KV cache,
is going to exceed your H100 memory.
And if you have B200s, you can increase the batch size more,
but eventually you hit some limit.
So there's limitations to how much
you can increase your throughput.
You'll never get to the asymptote
because you'll hit the memory.
And also, your throughput is getting--
your gains are kind of diminishing as well.
So increasing batch size worsens the latency
because now you have a larger KV cache to read and write.
And remember, it's batched.
So if you're an individual query,
you have to wait for everyone to finish.
So you have to basically-- you're waiting for a bus,
and the latency is pretty high.
You wait and then you go.
Whereas, the throughput of a bus is pretty good
because you can move everyone at once.
So the throughput improves as batch size increases
because, remember, the parameters are shared,
and you load that once into memory.
And you can process a lot of sequences.
So trade-off between latency and throughput,
just to make sure everyone's aligned—smaller batch sizes
use better latency but worse throughput.
Large batch sizes yield better throughput but worse latency.
OK.
I'm not going to really talk about parallelism too much.
There's also another dimension of inference,
which is you can shard your model
across multiple devices.
You can look at the scaling book chapter on inference
if you want to know more.
Just as a very trivial example, if you
launch M copies of the model, the latency is the same,
and the throughput increases by M.
And then the other metric we didn't talk about
is time to first token.
And this is essentially the time it
takes to do prefill because after you finish prefill,
then you can basically start generating.
So if you want to fast—
if you want faster TTFT, you should use smaller batch sizes,
and you want larger batch sizes to improve throughput.
So hopefully, that is clear.
Any questions about throughput and latency
and how they interact with each other?
OK.
So now that we have a conceptual framework for thinking
about how efficient inference is in terms of arithmetic intensity
and throughput and latency, now let's try to make it faster.
How do we make inference faster?
There's a bunch of different techniques which
are quite varied, ranging from changing the model architecture
to doing systems optimization and everything in between.
So inference in some sense is a fairly rich cross-cutting topic.
So the most maybe now in hindsight obvious thing
you can think about is hopefully beat it into your head
that memory is the bottleneck for inference,
and the KV cache takes up a lot of memory.
And it could even be larger than the number of parameters
if for a large enough batch size.
So let's just try to reduce the size of the KV cache.
Now, you have to be careful about how you do this
because you want to make sure you don't lose too
much accuracy in the process.
So here is one thing you can do, which we already talked about,
which is grouped query attention.
And just as a reminder here, so multi-headed attention--
basically for every token, you have
a key and a value and a query.
And if you do grouped query attention,
you basically compute the same number of queries,
but you have only a smaller number of groups,
and you compute key and value for each group.
So K is the number of groups here.
And so in the multi-headed attention, K is N, no reduction.
There's something called multi query attention, which no one
uses because it's really bad.
K equals 1.
And somewhere in between is hopefully
where we'll find a balance between accuracy and speed.
So this is the paper that introduces GQA from 2023.
And they show that if you look at time per sample, which
is related to both latency and throughput,
you see that the MHA-- so Multi-Head Attention.
Full attention has this high time.
Whereas, if you start K equals 1, it's much faster.
And then you can actually keep on increasing the K to K
equals 8, and it's still pretty good.
And eventually, your time goes up quite a bit.
So why does GQA improve latency and throughput?
Well, it reduces the KV cache by a factor of N over K. And just
as a friendly reminder, reducing memory usage leads to speed up
because we're memory-bound.
So let's revisit our friendly Llama model here.
Remember in the initial configuration,
we're just using K equals N. So there's
没有多头——是multi-head attention，
没有减少键和值的数量。
所以对于这个，记住使用batch size为64，
我们得到这个吞吐量和延迟。
现在如果你用GQA，我们要放入，比如说，
一种稀疏度为1/5。
这大幅减少了内存，
进而改善了延迟
并且也提高了吞吐量。
所以延迟和吞吐量并不总是相互矛盾的。
如果你减少内存量，它就会同时改善两者。
主要是batch维度允许的。
那是紧张的焦点。
好的。
所以这很好。
让我们实际上把batch size增加到更大
看看会发生什么。
所以之前，如果我们batch size为256，
我们就内存不足了。
但现在，它能装进内存了。
我们看到，延迟受到了一些影响，因为我们
增加了batch size，但吞吐量
成比例上升。
所以有时你要联合调整这些参数。
你可以减少KV cache，但那
允许你增加batch size
并允许做出其他权衡。
所以你必须做的最后一件事是，每当
你做一些有损的改变时，你要
确保准确率不会下降。
这篇论文表明，对于GQA，时间是更好的。
但在一系列评估中，基本上它运行良好。
所以现在有了这些准确率值，
我认为你总是要持保留态度
因为这是针对特定模型的。
后来，DeepSeek论文应该表明它实际上确实会有损害。
所以我想，把所有
不只是数学的东西都持保留态度吧。
好的。
所以说到DeepSeek，这里有另一个想法
to reduce the KV cache.
So the theme is reduce the KV cache and latency and throughput
improve.
So this is multi-headed attention,
same number of queries and keys and values for every token.
And GQA, remember, we have reduced the number of keys
and values for every token.
Sorry, not for every token.
We basically have reduced the number of values and keys.
And now, the multi-latent attention for DeepSeek
says we're actually going to leave the number of keys
and values the same one for every token essentially.
But I'm going to parameterize--I'm going to compress these.
So normally, you have some--
how do you compute your keys and values?
You have your activations, and you multiply them
by some matrix to get K and some other matrix to get V.
And these are generally N times H dimensions, like your model
dim, which is big.
So MLA says I'm going to actually project
these activations down into C dimensions.
So DeepSeek-V2 reduced it from 16,000 to 512,
so this is quite aggressive compression here.
And then I'm going to compute the k and the V
from this compressed representation.
So now, I can just store C. This is much smaller.
And then when I need my keys and values,
I can just materialize them.
So there is one wrinkle here, which
is that MLA is not compatible with rope,
which operates directly on the keys and values.
So what they do is add additional dimensions
for handling the rope.
But more or less, it's still a pretty big reduction.
So the latency and throughput improvements
follow by just simple math.
The smaller the KV cache, the faster you go.
It's almost kind of linear scaling up until at some point.
And then, remember, you need to check
whether your model is accurate.
So first of all, this is the result
that kind of contradicts or is in tension with the GQA paper.
They show that GQA actually isn't that great.
So this is MHA.
This is GQA.
These numbers are smaller than these numbers.
But they show that their method, MLA, Multi-Latent Attention
works even a little bit better than MHA.
But let's just say it's about the same.
So this column and this column are much better than—
I guess there's no GQA on this table.
You have to compare over here.
So I'll show you an— yeah.
How does this compare to reducing the number
of dimensions, the model?
So the question is, how does this
compare with reducing the dimension of the model?
So that's a good question.
These ablations don't show that.
My guess is that reducing the model dimension
just makes things worse because you're indiscriminately
just reducing everything.
I think the trick in all of this kind of
is to find places in the model where you can squeeze.
And this apiary, I don't think you
can necessarily know for sure.
You just have to do a bunch of experimentation
and see what works.
So here's another idea to reduce your KV cache.
This is called cross-layer attention.
So the idea is that normally, every layer has KV, K's and V's.
But let's say instead of doing that, we're just
going to compute KVs for a subset of the layers.
And then, just for this layer, I'm
just going to use the previous layers on KV cache.
So this is another way of sharing.
Just like GQA shares K across heads,
now I'm sharing KVs across layers.
And empirically, this paper shows that doing this
improves the Pareto frontier.
所以这些模型中的每一个都更好——
给定一种方法，你总是可以调整 KV
缓存的大小，通过改变 K 和 head 维度，我猜这
有点像你提到的改变模型维度的观点。
但如果你做这种 CLA 跨层注意力，它会更好。
那么继续，快速浏览不同的技术
来减少 KV 缓存。
有局部或滑动窗口注意力。
这是一个相当古老的想法
也是一个非常自然的想法。
所以如果你看完整的注意力矩阵，它是 N 的平方。
而不是那样做，如果你
要生成一个 token，你只需看最后 K 个 token。
所以你本质上有一个滑动窗口。
对于你生成的每个 token，你只依赖于最后 K 个。
现在，如果你这样做，有效的——
所以 KV 缓存现在与序列长度无关。
它只是批大小乘以其他变量，
这很棒。
这对于长上下文尤其棒。
现在，由于层数，
有效上下文长度实际上
大于所声明的上下文长度
因为信息可以传播得更远，如果
你沿着层向下走。
现在，你可以做更花哨的事情。
你可以也许不做密集的层选择，
但你可以把它间隔开。
你也可以做这种全局加滑动窗口
其中你有对固定的
不同 token 点的网格的注意力，加上一个局部滑动窗口。
所以你可以做各种事情。
现在，这个的问题是它实际上
仍然损害准确性。
所以这降低了表达能力。
这里没有免费的午餐，或者至少这
是一顿昂贵的午餐。
所以人们想出的解决方案
是他们将局部注意力与全局注意力交错。
所以这些混合模型对某些层有完整注意力
and some local layers for some of the other layers.
And you're basically always trying
to-- and then so that allows you to essentially reduce
the KV cache a little bit.
And you're always trying to balance accuracy with the speed.
Yeah.
Hybrid model-wise, is there a difference
between the trade-off in using a linear time invariant
versus a sliding window?
Yeah.
So the question is, what about linear attention versus sliding
window attention?
So I'm not going to talk about linear attention.
But very quickly, there's a bunch of methods where,
instead of storing KV cache, since you basically
compute some compressed representation of all the history.
So linear, the most naive linear attention
is you just sum the KV values up into a single vector.
So that's definitely independent of the sequence length.
You can do fancier things.
There's gated net, delta nets, and Mamba
which allows you to try to compress but not forget as much.
Now the question is, how do those compare?
Those have also been used in place
of sliding window attention, and people have gotten good results
with them.
You can also use a combination of full attention,
sliding window attention, and the linear attention
because they capture different aspects.
If you care about local high-resolution stuff,
then sliding attention is better.
If you just want broad summaries of the past,
then the other linear attention might be better.
So then for a long context sentence,
would you say your attention would
be a better setting for that?
So the question is, for long context with linear attention
be better?
So there's no free lunch, right?
Let's say you have a very long context,
and you're solving a needle in a haystack problem.
If you have to compress your entire history
into a small context, you're just going to lose information,
and you might just not be able to retrieve it.
I guess I feel like what it seems like people
go with hybrid architectures that you'll always
need some of longer attention, but I'm just
trying to understand in my head, what the trade-off between using
a sliding window versus some of a Mamba, delta net layer
would be.
Is using a delta net layer better
than using sliding window consistently?
Or what is the actual maybe representative trade-offs?
Yeah.
Maybe I'll say that the Mamba and delta net
are more powerful than the sliding window.
Attention maybe you can think about the Mamba
as probably can--
it certainly can represent some of the aspects of sliding window
attention because you can just-- as you're doing the recurrence,
it can just look at the last state.
So yeah, maybe you can think about the linear attention
or its extensions as being better.
They have more room.
Once you do sliding window attention, you're done.
There's nothing else you can-- Yeah.
OK.
So let me just quickly go through this.
Just highlight this DeepSeek.
DeepSeek continues to innovate different types of attention
mechanisms.
So remember, they came up with the multi-latent attention,
which compresses the key values.
There is this thing called--
now they have compressed sparse attention, DeepSeek
sparse attention, and heavily compressed attention.
I never remember all these acronyms and what they mean,
but let's look at this diagram.
So normally, have your KV tokens and your query token.
So compressed attention is going to basically compress
每 M 个令牌合并成一个令牌。
然后还有这个东西叫做
DeepSeek 稀疏注意力，它基本上是选择
其中的一个子集来保留。
而选择子集的方式是你实际上
计算一些 LiDAR 权重查询和键，
然后你做一次更小的注意力
来得到这些索引分数，这样你就知道要保留什么。
所以一个闪电般快速的方法来找出
你需要保留哪些令牌。
然后你使用那些。
然后还有一些更多的压缩发生。
所以为了节省时间，我继续往下讲。
这一节的目标是减少 KV 缓存，因为 KV
缓存与内存相关。
我们看到推理是内存受限的。
所以这直接转化为
吞吐量和延迟的改进。
关键在于做到这一点而不损害准确率。
所以你可以跨层做更低维度的 KV 缓存，
跨头和跨头维度。
你可以做局部注意力。
你可以做线性注意力，之前讨论过，
还有更多。
还有扩散模型，
这是一种非自回归的生成方式，
可以快得多。
好的。
所以让我们谈谈几个其他重要的想法。
所以量化更像是一个，我会
说，不太像是架构，而更像是
一种系统视角，关于如何让东西更小。
所以这里的关键思想就是降低数字的精度。
更少的内存意味着更高的延迟和吞吐量。
显然，你必须担心准确率。
所以量化——这里有很多选项，一路
从 bf16 一直到 int4。
所以你可以做的一件事，如果你
担心量化会搞砸你，
就是你训练模型时考虑量化。
这是量化感知训练。
在训练时的前向传播过程中，
你进行量化和反量化，基本上
在训练时模拟这些量化误差。
所以一般来说，现在权重
会朝着量化方向适配。
效果会更好。
但缺点是它需要昂贵的大规模训练。
所以通常人们的做法是先训练模型，
然后再事后量化。
这就是训练后量化。
它通常便宜得多。
有一种朴素的做法是，对每一层或张量，
你基本上为每个张量确定缩放因子和零点，
比如说，张量。
然后你分别量化它。
这通常效果不太好。
你可以使用一种叫 GPTQ 的方法，
它利用一些 Hessian 信息来逐层量化，
逐层进行。
然后你跟踪那些传播到
未量化权重中的误差。
这样就能让你校正这些误差。
而激活感知量化
是一种更复杂的方法，其观察是
某些激活通道很大，
那些与这些通道交互的权重更重要。
所以让我们给这些权重分配更多精度。
让我们看看这张图。
通常，如果你取一个 fp16 权重矩阵，
然后量化它，你会得到——比如说
你把它量化到 int3。
但你要做的是找出
哪些是活跃的？
所以这些可能是激活通道。
其中一些激活通道很大。
所以如果它们总体上很大，那么你
基本上为这个通道分配，比如说，fp16。
其余的都保持为三。
对于少数重要通道，你使用更高精度。
So another idea here is to do model pruning.
So here you just take a large model,
and you rip out pieces of it, and you fix it up.
It's a very crude way, but it turns out to work.
So there's this paper from NVIDIA where, essentially—
let me actually—let's see.
So you first have to estimate the importance
of the different parts of the model
and choose the most important parts.
And then you basically remove different hidden units
and different even layers.
And now, we have a model.
It's not going to be very good.
And so what you do is you post-train it.
You train it some more on the data or the tasks
that you care about to heal it.
So this is, in some sense, a training way to reduce the KV
cache, but where you initialize it with parts of a good model.
So this seems to work pretty well.
So they were able to take a 15B model and reduce it to an 8B
model.
And it doesn't really hurt accuracy by too much.
And the amount that you use to train the model
or through this process is much less.
OK.
So just to summarize here, the game
is to reduce the inference complexity
without hurting accuracy.
You can think about this as mostly reducing the number
of parameters or CPU cache.
You can define a faster model architecture to train it,
or you can define a faster model architecture.
Initialize the weights from original model, which
might have a different architecture,
but you just make this Frankenstein thing,
and then you repair the faster model with distillation.
OK.
Yeah.
Could you say more about how you distinguish the important
from the unimportant layers?
So how do you distinguish the important layers
So in general, you have a calibration set,
and you pass the inputs through the model.
And you're basically looking at the magnitude
of the activations.
And the ones that are-- some of them,
especially if they're dead units, will be kind of close to 0.
And the ones that are large, you want to keep.
So that's a high-level idea.
I guess why does it matter if the activation is high?
It could just be like-- what if it's
just always high, for instance?
Or is that--
So the question is, what if all the activations are high?
So in general, this is a kind of an empirical observation
that some of the channels will be much higher than others.
If this weren't true, then these techniques wouldn't necessarily
work, but it happens to be true because that's
how these models ended up being trained.
And then you can exploit that.
Say a neuron, which is always value
100 across all the samples.
Would that mean that it's necessarily meaningful?
Or maybe it's just an artifact of training
that I'm just like [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, I see.
So the question is, what if a neuron is always 100?
I mean, if that's the case, you can also look
at variance-related questions.
If it's 100, you can't just remove it
because then everything is going to be broken.
If it's high mean and low variance,
maybe there's another way to just incorporate the bias
essentially.
OK.
Let me quickly go through this other idea.
So far, we've looked at lossy methods which basically
really crunch down the KV cache, but it could hurt accuracy.
This is a very elegant way of doing this in a lossless way.
This is called speculative sampling or speculative decoding.
So remember that if you're doing prefill,
you can encode all the tokens in parallel.
This also gives you probabilities.
This is fast.
This is compute-bound and all nice things.
And in generation, it's one at a time.
So checking is faster than generation.
If I give you a sequence, it's fast to tell me
how good it is, much faster than it is to generate one at a time.
So you can exploit this asymmetry using the following idea.
So what we're going to do is use a cheap draft model
to basically generate from the guess a few tokens,
let's say four tokens.
And then we're going to use the model we actually care about,
the target model Q, which is to basically review these tokens
and accept or not accept them.
So things are kind of chosen to be balanced.
The draft model is just smaller and cheaper.
And so even though it's memory-bound,
and it has to generate one at a time, it's not too bad.
Whereas, the target model is big and expensive,
but what we're doing is asking it
to process a batch of tokens in parallel
so it won't also be too bad.
OK, so here's the video that shows how things work.
So if you use a big model token by token,
it's going to be pretty slow.
But if you are doing speculative decoding,
then you can see the small model generating a bunch of tokens,
and then the large model basically critiquing them.
And then, so you basically can get this burst
of tokens and then maybe another burst of tokens
and so on and so forth.
OK.
So here is the algorithm for-- there's
a few papers that came out with speculative decoding
around the same time.
This is one of them.
And so the idea here is that in order to generate,
we're going to generate K tokens.
And we're just going to sample from this draft model.
So p is the draft model.
We're going to sample K tokens.
And then in parallel, we're going
to compute the logits of these draft tokens using q.
And then now we have to determine whether we accept or not.
And this is where you do a bit of math and probability
and statistics.
You basically are going to accept with probability min 1
over this ratio of q over p.
So if q is much larger than p, the larger the q is,
the more likely you want to accept it.
And otherwise you sample from this residual distribution
and exit.
So this is basically rejection sampling
except for rejection sampling.
Sometimes when you reject you get nothing.
But here we always are guaranteed
to get an exact sample from the target model.
I'm going to skip this simple proof.
It's basically the same arguments
as rejection sampling to show that it's
the exact probabilities from the target model.
And the initial paper shows that this is fast.
And generally, if you have too few draft tokens,
you're not really leveraging the batching on the target model
side.
And if you have too many, then you're
going to reject more often.
So there's a sweet spot around, in this case, three or four.
And in general, the draft model is much smaller
than the target model.
And ideally, you want the draft model
to be as close to the target, which
means that you want to distill it,
which means that actually a lot of the same ideas that we just
talked about are applicable to speculative decoding as well.
So basically, the idea is that let's try
to reduce your KV cache via all the different shenanigans.
and if you end up with a model you're happy with,
just serve that.
if you're not happy with it, then
it at least can be a draft model, and you can use your main model
to fix things up.
there's a whole literature
on speculative decoding right now
that improve over the original, which I'll skip for now.
so very quickly now, dynamic workloads.
so this is the use case, is you're serving a live website,
and users come and chat with your model.
the requests arrive at different times.
they have different shared prefixes,
and they have different lengths.
so it's pretty messy.
it's far from this very simple training where
you have these blocks of the same number of tokens
all at once.
so what do you do in this case?
so there's this idea-- there's a system called
Orca that was built. this is actually
very early on which introduced this idea
of continuous batching.
so the idea is that you get a bunch of requests
that look like this.
so here's a prefix of the first request,
and you're generating this token.
here's the second one.
here's the third one, the fourth one.
it's jagged because every prefix has a different length.
and what we're going to do is we're
going to decode step by step.
so every step you decode one token for all the sequences.
next step, you decode another token for all the sequences.
and then if you end, you just eject that sequence.
and then as new requests arrive to the batch,
then you basically put it in the batch,
and then you just continue.
so that's why it's called continuous batching because it's
this batch is dynamically being updated
with either old finished sequences being evicted
and new ones coming in.
So now, one problem here is that everything
we've seen batching works when all the sequences have
the same dimensionality.
You have tensors.
Every slice has the same dimensionality.
But if your request here has a different length,
so what do you do about that?
So there's this idea called selective batching
where let's say you have a length 3, length 9, and a length
5.
So here in the attention computation,
you can't really do anything about this
because attention depends on the length of your sequence.
So if you have a 3 by 3, a 9 by 9 computation,
you can't really share the tensor effectively.
But for the non-attention, the MLP layers,
which take up a lot of FLOPs, you can actually just
concatenate all the sequences together
to form a mega sequence, and you process that.
So the final idea is page attention.
This was introduced in the PagedAttention paper.
Of course, PagedAttention has many other bells and whistles now,
but this is the core idea at that time.
So the question is, how is the KV cache stored?
So if you think about requests coming in,
you have to put them in memory somewhere.
And in general, there's this problem
that you get fragmentation.
This is what happens to--
or used to happen to your hard drive.
And you have to defrag your hard drive back in the day.
So there's two types of fragmentation.
One is that you have to allocate enough buffer so
that-- because you don't know when you're going to stop.
So you might have a max token limit of 1,024.
So you have to allocate all this memory.
And you can't put anything in there
because you're going to just generate
until you hit the max tokens, and that's very wasteful.
That's internal fragmentation.
And then there's also, you have-- there could be space
between different requests.
And that space is maybe too small to get used effectively.
So that's just wasted space.
So the solution here is, these are systems people.
So they know their operating systems.
They said, OK, well we've solved this problem once before,
so let's just use the same idea here.
So we're going to divide the KV cache of a sequence
into non-contiguous blocks, OK?
So if you have this sequence, four score and seven years
ago our fathers brought forth, we're
just going to chunk it up into these blocks of size 4.
Doesn't matter where the blocks go, but they're
going to be aligned according to the block.
So there's some uniformity there.
So when two requests share the same--
can actually share the same KV cache.
So you might have this block and this block.
So this block might go here and here,
and this block might be over there.
So they're interspersed.
But as long as you have the indices
and keep track of where everything is, it's fine.
So in particular, if you have system prompts, then
you can actually just cache these system prompts,
the KV cache and the system prompts, once.
And that can be useful for all the queries, OK?
So this is very useful because if a lot of people
are using the same system prompt,
then you don't have to compute the cache for every request.
Also there are many applications where you have the same prompt,
and you actually want to generate multiple responses.
So in that case, you can also just share
the KV cache for the prompt and just
have unique responses coming out.
OK, so for example, if you were to generate,
let's say, multiple generations from score
and seven years ago are, blank, and so what would happen here
is that you would have score and seven.
And you would start by having years ago or our.
And then this is called copy on write semantics.
You keep this.
And then we have these two samples.
And if they had happened to sample let's say the same token,
you just continue with that.
But if they sample different tokens, you split the block,
and then you can continue there.
So you're basically sharing as much of the prefix cache
as you can.
There's a bunch of other optimizations like kernels
that I'm not going to have time to go over.
But the general idea is that you're
using these operating systems metaphors to manage
your inference.
So summary here-- inference is really, really important.
It's very different from training.
Even though it's the same model, but you're asking the model
to do something very different, ends up being very memory-bound.
And it's also dynamic if you're in a live chatbot use case.
We saw a variety of different techniques to improve inference.
You can quantize.
You can come up with new architectures.
You can prune and distill.
You can also use speculative sampling.
But all of these are driven by the same principle
here, which is reduce your KV cache
but don't hurt accuracy too much.
And then there's ideas from systems like paging
and speculative execution that can
be brought to bear for actually live inference servers.
One thing we didn't really get a chance to talk about,
which was discussed briefly, is that I
think that new architectures have actually a huge potential
for improvement, things like state space models
or linear attention or diffusion.
At some level, the KV cache and the way
that attention is built fundamentally
makes it an inference-unfriendly kind of architecture.
So if you can come up with a new architecture that
is designed for inference in the way
that the transformer was not, this can maybe unlock a lot.
OK, so I will stop there.
And next class, Tatsu will return and talk
about scaling laws part 2.